All right then everyone, in the past video we had a look at what is scope defined at
different levels, four levels of scope actually, and then what are packages? Why do we use them?
And then in this video we are going to look at how do we use packages? How do we declare them?
How do we import them? And what relation do they have with the scope? And we're back to our
IDE that is intelligent and created this class scope work. Public static void main is ready.
And now there is this is where we would, we would demonstrate packages. And as you have
look at the first line, it says package org dot w aq. This is the package that we've been
following all along the scores, right? So now we'll zoom into this and this will just make you clear
what are we after here, right? So what does this say is, how do you define a new package in a class
with the keyword package? And first things first, we should never put in classes without packages,
although we can, but that's never recommended because code is not organized. And you know that
debugging is difficult and and would end up in a lot of problems later on. So we should always
put in packages. That's what we have been following. But now we are having a look at why do we do
that? So how do we do that? So in a class in a file, in a Java file, how do you declare a new package
with the keyword package? And then the identifier and through cable case packages should be in all
smalls. And like we're following here, super package dot sub package, or you could have just
called it, you would have just called it whack. That's fine as well, right? But generally you will see
super package dot sub package dot sub package. That's the kind of syntax we write. And that's why
I'm following it here. And the industry standard is we do that in reverse domain. Let's say
you're working at TCS. So you'll just say calm dot TCS dot training. You're working at society
general. You'll say calm dot soggen dot learning. You're working. Let's say at Google, you will
not say google dot com dot training, com dot Google dot development, right? So reverse domain is the
industry standard. That's what we are sticking to here. So org dot wag is fine. Now whatever class
you will put in in this fight will belong to this package because the rule is a Java file can have
only one package statement declaration. And it should be at the top. Again, a Java file can have
only one package statement declaration. And it should be at the top. And that's why we're having it
here. I cannot have a package down the line. I can't say for example, package other that's an arrow
here. It says if you hover on this class or interface, expect it not a package because it can just be
only months and at the very first line. So whatever classes you put in here like public class scope
work, let's say I have another class, for example, I'll just call other and let's say this as just
one method, wide funk. So now this class also belongs to this package org dot wag. And behind the scenes
on your physical directory, they would both be a part of the folder org dot wag. So
that's how you declare packages. I come to how do you import them in some while. But starting with
the first scope, and that is the package private scope, which is by default. As you're seeing
this class, I made it as public. But this class doesn't have a scope. This means it has package
private scope, which is the default scope in Java. And this method, main always has to be public.
That means main has public scope, but funk doesn't have a scope written explicitly. That means
it has the default scope and what is that again, package private. Now, let's have a look at what
does it mean for you to define your types or your members as package private. That is default,
right? And again, package private scope can be put in at the class level interface level
or at the member level. You know, the members now, right? The instance variables of a class
as well as the methods, right? So package private is applicable at two levels, right? Right here,
right here. And within a class at the member level as well, local variables, local variables,
we cannot scope their right. None of the scope applies there because they already have a scope,
their local or their local to that method or local to that block in which they are defined.
Right. So now what does it mean? All right. So now for example, if you want to access this funk of
other inside main, obviously, I'll just have a sound message, a sample message, I'll say inside one.
If you want to call it at line number five, what is the syntax to do that? Just go on a recollect,
we had a look at that when we were talking about classes and objects, it remains the same,
right? But now we are seeing if it would be called or not, right? We do not take it for granted now
because we're talking about scope. And I'll say, for example, obviously, I need to create an
other object, I'll say new other, and you'll see other dot punk, is it accessible? It is why
now, let's have a look at that. See, fun defined in other is package private, other is package
private, you're accessing it in main, right? So what does it mean for you to define? It has
package private, that is, and you can take a note here or just remember it, package private
members of a class, or even the class itself, right? They're accessible right across the package
in which they are defined, but not outside of the package. That's why they're called private
to that package, right? See, package private. So package private members of a class or the class
itself or the interface itself, they are accessible right across the package in which they are
displayed within other classes as well, but which belong to the same package, but they cannot be
access outside of the package. And why are they accessible here? Because other and scope work
are both defined in the package, all dot whack, right? So other can be accessed here,
funk is again, package private, it can be accessed here. Now, you know, why does this work? All right.
And if you want to have different classes, but belong into the same package, but not in this file,
you can just go on and define them in a new file, but the first line should be
all dot whack, see, as is a response, calculate addition, conditional logic, all of them are part
of the all dot whack. That means all of them can access funk of other and funk. That's it. That's
how I have to access a method of loops work right here. I can do that if that is also defined as
package private. That's how package private works. That is private to the package. All right.
So the second scoop in Java that we are going to talk about is protected and protected has a
slight difference with package private, but significant, right? And protected the first thing
about protected is it cannot be it's only accessible or the scope is only applicable at the
member level, never at the class level. There is no such concept as a protected class in Java,
right? We can do that with inner classes, but let's leave that discussion for another day,
another video. But for now, protected, that is it cannot be applicable here just within the class,
either with instance variables or methods, but never at the class level. If you try to do that,
you should get an error. And that's what you do. You hover on this says modifier protected
not allowed here. So at the class level, by the way, a class can either be package private,
which is default or it can be public, nothing else. No other scopes are applicable here. All right.
So now what does it mean for you to define your members as package private? What does it really mean?
I said they have a slight difference, a minimal difference with package private members,
but significant yet. And what is that? So package private members of a class like protected members
or I'll just reference it all the way down. So protected members of a class like package
private members are accessible right across the package in which they are defined,
but this is a very bug, but big but here, but they can also be accessed outside of the package
in a special scenario of inheritance. And again, for iteration, I'll just put it down for you
can just take a note of this. That is protected members of a class like package private members
are accessible right across the package in which they are defined, but they're also accessible
outside of the package through inheritance within subclasses through inheritance within subclasses.
That's the only difference here. Right. And let's try to do that. What I'll say is I'll say
this class other and white fund this time it is protected. See, it makes no difference if you
access it within the package in under the class, it is still accessible. Right. But if you try to access
it outside of the package, let's in fact try to do that. What I'll say is I'll just go on and
on Java now I'll say new package. Let's just call it org dot for example work.
The first one was org dot back. This is org dot work. Let's create a new class in org dot work
and I'll just call it for example task. See, this is in org dot work. Now see shows with this.
All others are in whack. This one is in another sub package called work and what I'm trying to
do here is it doesn't have me, but or let's say it has me. I am calling it for me and I want to call
I want to call where did that go scope work. I want to call
others funk from outside of the package in task. Right. So the first thing, obviously the syntax
remains the same. What is the way to access it is the same. Can it be accessed? That's what we are
going to discuss here. So I'll just say other to new other and I'll say other errors at both lines
exactly the same syntax which worked in on line number five and six is now giving you an error
at five and six inside task inside another package. Why is that you hover on that and this error
isn't even related to scope. Right. It says that I don't understand which other you're talking about
because a class outside of the package isn't even visible. It isn't even found. Right. How can
you create an object out of it? Right. So the first step is to import that and how do we import it?
We say something like this. I say import org dot wack dot other that particular class. Right.
So that's the way to import after the package to the declaration. You say import and then
package dot sub package dot the class name. Otherwise, the alternative is you can just say start
start means all import every class from org dot wack. But that's not recommended because
think about it in a real world enterprise great project. There might be hundreds of classes in this
package. If we just put in an overburden on the on the system. Right. So always import the classes
that you want to work with. And here I want to work with other. Now, this is the way to import it,
but you're seeing still an error at line number two. Now, it knows that there is a class inside
org dot wack, which I'm trying to import. That's fine, but it isn't it isn't visible. Why it should
tells you other org dot wack to other is not public in org dot wack cannot be accessed from outside
package. What did I tell you? That is package private things can only be accessed within the same
package, but not in other packages. And for this to work, obviously, if this doesn't work, if
you're not able to import it, how can you create an object? How can you call a method? So for this to work,
we'll say we'll go to other and make this as public. Right. And now, an error, what does it say?
It says that class other is public should be declared in a fine name. Other don't Java.
Now, this is another error, another reason. And what is that? That is a Java file can have only one
public class, and that should be in the name of that file. But in this case, I have two
published classes in this file that cannot be because Java doesn't allow multiple public classes
to be in the same file, but as many as non public classes. And the one that has the public
specified with it has to be the name of your file. So what I'll do is I'll just get rid of this
here and in org.wag, create a separate file. I'll call it other. And I'll just paste it.
Right. Works fine. Public class other still in org.wag, but in a file of its own. Right. And I
can have this as public here. I can have scope work as public as well. No problems there. It still
works because you're accessing it within the same package. But when you try to access it,
outside the package in a different class. Now the error goes away. Right. We can import it because
it's public. We can create an object of out of it. It is public, but doesn't mean that
focus till accessible. Why? Because scope. And that's the beauty of scope in Java. It is resolved
by two levels in Java. The first is the top level that is the class level. And then the member
level and think about a great analogy that is your home. Just because you have opened the main gate
to everyone doesn't mean everyone can enter inside your bedrooms and use your washrooms or any other
room. Right. You still can control who gets access to coming into your bedroom who gets access to
coming into your lobby and washrooms. Right. So this one was open. That is the main gate at the class
level. Now the individual rooms are still closed. Why? Because funk as you saw is still defined
as protected. It cannot be accessed outside of the package. Right. So that is by this error.
But if you were able, if you were just trying to access it within the same package, you would have
been there. Right. So that is we still can't access it. I'll say. Why? Because it is defined as
protected. So you would need to define that also as public or or the second thing is as a
two new protected members can be accessed outside of the package as well through inheritance within
subclasses. So I don't want to keep this as public because if I keep it as public public means
universal access. Right. I still want to give access to someone in a restricted manner of inheritance
and I can do that. How I'll say go to other and I'll say this is protected by one. That's fine.
Task. I'll say extends. Other. I'll do the inheritance here. And just bear with me for a few
for some time because we have not covered inheritance yet. But that's how we do inheritance. We're
going to take it again with scratch from scratch. But for now, that's how we do inheritance in Java.
Task extends so that this becomes the child class. This becomes the parent class. Right. But it's
still an error because you forgot the ending point I said protected members of a class can be
accessed outside of the package within subclasses. But only through inheritance. What does inheritance mean
inheritance means as if the child class has a member as if it's its own. Right. It's deriving
it from a super class. But as if the member is its own, that means you would have been able to call
it. If you would have been accessing it with its own object, that's new task. Now works.
Spend some time here after this video is done and think what is happening here. Right.
Protected members can still be accessed out of the package. But in a special scenario,
that is two inheritance in subclasses. So we did the subclass, but then this is inheritance. This
is not because you're still calling it with the super class object. No, if you call it from the
child class object, if it is accessible, you know, we are in for a special situation. And now that's
the difference between protected and and package private. And you can put the protected
specified with instance variables as well as I said, it applies to both members, methods and
instance variables. And that's how it works. So now the third level of scope in Java is public.
We already had a look at it. That is if it was public, if this was public, then we did not need
to subclass it. We did not need to do anything else. It would be importable. And you can just go on
and call it because public means universal. It can be access right through the package. It can
be accessed in other classes and other packages. You don't need to do anything different. That's
perfectly fine. All right. And the last scope, which is the most restricted scope in Java is private.
And guess what private cannot be even accessed outside of the class in which it is declared,
how can it be accessed from outside the package? That means, for example, if you had this other
here. And for example, I declared a variable, private int length. And by the way, our instance
variables of a class should always be declared private more on that later. But for now, just
know that I've declared this as private. I'll tell you the reason why I said that in later
video. But for now, it later as private, it can't be accessed even in the same package outside,
outside the class. Let's say this is last another. I have a method white, do.
And I am trying to access length. I'll say new other, which I can do dot length.
It's equal to 90. What does it say? You hover on this. So it's length as private,
access, and all back either cannot even be accessed from outside the class in the same package,
remember, right? So these are the four levels for now. I'll just come in this, right? These are the
full levels of scope in Java out of these three are just keywords, right? And I'll just
try to create a table, which would be self-explanatory. That is which is accessible.
Where, but that is about scope in Java, right? At the class level, only two scopes apply,
that is a package private or public, there is no such concept as a protected or a private class
in Java, right? Then at the member level, all four scopes apply. I'll see you in the next video.
But, but as I said, just pause things, spend some time thinking about scope, try to manipulate
my code, try to tinker with it, and then see how playful you can get.